Let us also discuss a bit more syntax today.
And essentially, this will be more stuff on
programming by case distinction.
So, this is of course an important aspect for
defining functions.
We have seen this before and we have used
it in exercises.
And so far, this has been by "if-then-else"
expressions.
You might even have had reasons in your exercise
tasks to nest if-then-else expressions.
And once you start doing that, this becomes
a bit cumbersome.
So, there are other options, and some of them
will be discussed now (so more ways of doing
case distinction).
And Actually, this will not be finished today.
So, pattern-matching (and this is also
one way of programming by case distinction
in Haskell) will be handled in a different
week.
But let's first look at the situation with
if-then-else again and what we can do if this
takes too much nesting.
First, remember how an if-then-else looks.
So, that was an example that I used last week.
And you have done similar things in the exercises.
So, in a function definition on the right-hand
side (as an expression), we can use if-then-else.
There must be a condition and then two expressions.
They must be of the same type, otherwise it
wouldn't make sense.
And they must always both be there.
So, we cannot, for example, omit the "else",
because then this wouldn't evaluate to some
reasonable value or some value at all.
This was the Haskell syntax, and I explained
this as corresponding to this mathematical syntax.
So far, so good.
Now, as soon as I just mentioned, as soon as you have
more than one condition, or you have more
complex conditions, then on this side you
would have to nest an if-then-else expression.
So, maybe in the "then" branch you will have
to have another "if-then-else" to check the
second condition.
And this quickly becomes not so nice.
Of course, in mathematics, there is a different
approach.
In mathematics, in an expression like this,
people tend to write more than two cases.
So, we have the one case, another case, and
another case, ..., and then maybe the "else" case.
So, they don't nest these kinds of
expressions, they simply give a longer list
of conditions and expressions here.
Something like this can be mirrored in Haskell
as well.
So, that could look like this.
You probably haven't seen this definition
kind before, except if you have used HLint
and it has suggested it, which it tends to
do for nested if-then-else.
So, this could be an example we are viewing
again: compute some "scene" from a time parameter.
And maybe there are more complex conditions
than simply, if t is smaller than this, then
... else ..., or maybe there are more conditions.
So, we could have something like this.
And actually, if you just read this, you probably
know what is meant here.
So, under the condition that t is smaller than pi, smaller or equal
pi, we should do something.
Under the condition that that is not the case,
but t is actually greater than pi but less-equal
than the double of pi, then we should have
something else.
And under a third condition, namely that t
is actually greater than 2*pi, then yet another
expression should be evaluated.
So, this is also a way of expressing conditional
behaviour, and it very directly corresponds
to what mathematicians like to write.
Here is a function definition f(x) = ..., and
then maybe also three mutually exclusive conditions
on the x value.
And depending on what we have here, we get
different expressions.
Now, just as here, we could write any Boolean
condition: anything that can be evaluated
or checked in mathematics.
Here we can write anything that is of Boolean
type.
So often of course, these will be comparisons
like here, or combinations of comparisons.
But that need not be the case.
You could have written any expression which
evaluates to a Boolean.
It doesn't have to be arithmetic comparisons
combined with "and" and "or" etc.
You can write anything here, any predicate,
anything which evaluates to a Boolean value.
And as I already mentioned, once you start
writing nested if-then-else expressions,
HLint will suggest writing things like this.
This HLint is a component inside Autotool.
So, you will benefit from these suggestions
also in Autotool without using HLint as a
separate tool.
Let us discuss some more details, in particular
about, for example, the order in which we
write conditions like this.
So, these conditions are called guards.
This is expressing a function with guards.
And a guard is this kind of Boolean expression
that can be written here.
In if-then-else it's clear what happens: You
have "if" and then you either do the left
or the right, the "then" or the "else".
So, there is no question of order because
the "then" and the "else" are clear about
in which cases they execute (or the corresponding
expression is evaluated).
Here, we now of course at least have to ask
what happens if, for example, these guards
overlap.
Or does it matter in which order you write
them down?
So i will discuss this on the factorial example,
which is also a very simple example for recursion,
of course.
So, the factorial function as defined in mathematics.
It could be written with an if-then-else of course or via if-then-else(s), but mathematically or more mathematically looking, you
would write:
The factorial of an integer is 1 if the
integer is zero (that is the starting of the
factorial function), and if the argument is
greater than zero, then you want to compute
n times factorial of the predecessor.
That looks reasonable.
Now what about the order of the clauses?
So, does it matter in which order I write
these things down?
Well, it depends on the conditions of course.
In this case here, these two conditions they are
mutually exclusive:
There is no n input possible that would
both be zero and greater than zero.
And since that is the case, the following
variant, where I simply switched the two lines
here, is equivalent.
Because simply the value of n will decide
which of them is taken, and the order in which
these are written down does not matter.
Now I will consider further examples where
I change the guards, etc.
And what I would have done in the past is
to have a separate window open, in which I
have this program in Haskell and always edit the
program, and let it run to see the effects
of changing the order of things and changing
conditions in the guards, etc.
I don't want to do this now, because that
would be too much stopping and restarting
my video recording.
So, what I suggest, if you want to follow
the arguments here, is that you do this yourself.
You can stop the video and copy the code into
an editor window and then run this in GHCi,
here is all the versions that I discussed.
So, here I will simply say what happens and
you can check yourself (if you have copied
the code).
But I will not actually demonstrate this here
for all the versions.
I will simply talk about this.
So, probably this will be a bit shorter than
if i like I have done in the past.
In this example, we will see:
No matter which of these two versions we see
here is taken, if you run it on something
like 12 or whatever, some nice non-negative
number (here you see already that negative
numbers might be a problem, but if it only check or if we only
call "factorial" on non-negative inputs),
then these two versions that we see here and
here, behave the same.
What if the guard conditions overlap?
So, if you don't have that simply the input
value is uniquely determining which of the
two lines is taken?
This could correspond to changing that greater
(>) from the previous slide to greater-equal
(>=).
Then suddenly there is a difference.
Suddenly, this version still works fine, but
this one is problematic.
Maybe you can already guess what would happen,
or you can check on the side, what happens
if you take this code and run it again maybe
with input 12.
What you should see is a runtime error.
Why is that?
Well, if you run this and you start with 12, then
12 is greater-equal 0; then you will have
12 * factorial of 11.
And then 11 is again in this case.
So, it is 11 * factorial 10.
This goes down, down, down, ... until factorial
0.
And then what happens is that factorial 0 would
match the second case.
But actually, Haskell will evaluate these
from top to bottom.
So, it will first check whether the first guard
is satisfied.
And for the input "n = 0", actually this first
guard is satisfied, because 0 is greater-equal
0.
So, what will happen is: 0 * factorial (-1).
And actually, Haskell will not somehow magically
say: "Well, 0 * something is irrelevant."
Instead, it will actually try to compute factorial
of -1.
And then for factorial of -1, if you go again
into the recursion, then we have -1, and -1
is not greater or equal to 0.
So, what is factorial (-1)?
We don't know.
The compiler doesn't know.
The runtime system doesn’t know.
So, there will be a runtime error.
This doesn't happen here.
Why not?
Because here it is not the case that once
we have factorial of zero, we again make a
recursive call.
Because evaluating/checking from top to bottom,
factorial of zero will match the first case.
So, the output will be 1.
And then the recursion stops.
So, if you have a base case like here, then
this base case should be first in such a sequence
of checks.
Sometimes, the compiler will be able to warn
about cases like this, because essentially,
the runtime error that we get from this is
that this is not fully defined.
Integers contain negative numbers, but for
negative numbers we don't give a case.
Sometimes, the compiler will be able to warn
about this.
Okay, but let's say we don't make this mistake.
Let's say we stay with the correct order.
What is the problem, then?
Well, we don't have the problem that if we start
with 12, we get to zero and then 0 * factorial
(-1).
We don't get this problem.
But if we, right away, call this function
with -1, we again have a runtime error.
So, if we call with -1, then neither the base
case matches nor the recursive case.
So, we get a runtime error.
As mentioned before, with appropriate settings,
the compiler can warn us of this.
And in Autotool, we will henceforth enable
these warnings, so that if you program with
guards, for example, and you are not careful
to make sure that there's always a case that
matches, then the compiler will complain.
The compiler, of course, cannot know for sure
whether you have matched all cases.
So, the compiler will be overcautious.
So, it might warn you even though actually,
with some mathematical insight, one can see
that your code is covering all cases.
The compiler tries to warn you about cases
where it doesn't know, because it can't tell,
that you have covered all cases.
One way to make sure that you covered all
cases, and also to let the compiler be certain
that you've covered all cases, is that you
have something like a catch-all clause.
Like in the example from before, instead of having
two conditions, one being n==0 and the other
being something like n>0 or n>=0, you could
say "otherwise".
Then, checking from top to bottom, for every
input that is not zero this last line will
be taken.
At least then we won't have a runtime error,
in the sense that for some input, the factorial
function doesn't know what to compute.
So, now in GHCi, this wouldn't lead to a runtime
error.
Of course, it could still be a problem if
you call with negative values, but then not
because of a runtime error (of a missing case),
but actually because of non-termination.
Because then, you will run (if you call this
with negative inputs) into an infinite recursion.
Because you never stop for negative values.
But that is a separate problem.
And of course, a problem that no compiler
can, in general, catch; simply because of
the "halting problem".
That was this observation.
In this case, negative inputs would be a problem.
We could also fix this in some sense by saying:
We take the base case whenever we have a non-positive
value; not only for zero, but also for negative
values.
Now this would be something which passes the
compiler, because the compiler can tell that
we have covered all cases.
It also never has a problem at runtime in
terms of not knowing which case to take, precisely
because of this last case.
So, the compiler guarantees this.
Then it's true that you never run out of cases
to consider, so to say, because the "otherwise"
case always applies.
And it also doesn't have a non-termination
problem, simply because at some point after
reducing this many times, or right away if
called with a negative value, we will always
reach this base case (either immediately or after
a finite number of steps).
So, some lessons here:
The order matters in selecting which line
to take.
The semantics will consider the order.
That also means that we can exploit this order.
So, we can maybe simplify some later conditions.
We will see this in an example in a moment.
We can simplify some later conditions since/if
we know that the preceding guards have already
been checked.
Exhaustiveness matters because we want to
avoid runtime errors.
Now, some further remarks.
The compiler checks ahead of time are nice,
but they are not perfect.
They can't be perfect because of, for example,
"the halting problem".
So, it's impossible in general to detect infinite
recursion, for example, but also some other
problems that a program might have.
Haskell does a pretty good job of preventing
preventable errors, but it can't fix all problems.
Even the simpler checks that are not aiming
for perfection are not as powerful as one
might sometimes hope.
Sometimes, from some mathematical insight
into your problem, you might think the compiler
should be able to tell that a certain definition
is exhaustive.
But sometimes that's not happening, and for
a good reason.
Here is an example.
It will warn you against trying to rely on
certain properties, about relations from mathematics,
for example.
You might think that if you write a condition
like this, f x y is: if x and y are equal,
then something, and if x and y are not equal,
then something else; you might assume that
this would be statically safe.
Well, the compiler won't be able to tell that
this is safe because "basically, these two
things are opposites of each other, so only
and exactly one of them will be true".
That is a reasonable thing to assume, but
actually not so simple.
There is a good reason why this is not considered
safe in general by the compiler.
And the reason is that certainly this is true
(that in these two things, always one of them
will be true) for base types like numbers,
characters, or strings; but actually, in Haskell
you can overload equality and inequality for
your own types, and nobody can prevent you
as a programmer from writing a new type with
equality and inequality checks, where there
are some pairs of values x and y where neither
of these two conditions is true.
And then the compiler cannot promise that
one of them will always be true.
Maybe it's not even the case for your own
type.
So, in that sense, it's better to, again,
replace the second condition by "otherwise",
because then also the compiler can say that
definitely one of the two cases will be applicable.
Also, in an ideal world, we wouldn't depend
so much on massaging our guard conditions.
So, let's return to this issue, where we had
problems with negative inputs.
And the fix was to switch from "n==0" to "n≤0"
in the first case, because then we would have
covered all cases and also didn't run into
infinite recursion for negative inputs.
One might argue that this is not what one
wants, to have this factorial function return
one for all negative numbers, if you change
to "n≤0" here.
So, the real fix (the conceptually most appealing
fix) would be to use the type system to even
prevent that you get negative inputs here right?.
So, the Integer type contains negative numbers,
but one could use a more expressive type system
which actually can guarantee that the factorial
function will, in a given program, never be
called on negative numbers.
That is possible, but it
is really a topic for another lecture, and
maybe not even for this course.
It is actually for another course or seminar
or an advanced lecture, not necessarily this
semester.
I just wanted to mention that such a more
static fix is also possible.
But let's not go in this direction.
Let's for now apply our insights we gained
from discussing the factorial example to the
situation we considered earlier.
We had the "scene" function.
And mathematically, I wrote it like this:
I check whether t is smaller-equal to pi,
then I check the next period from pi to 2*pi,
and then above 2*pi (this could be something
that I want to express).
Now given what we know about the order of evaluation of
checking of such guards, and what we know about
exhaustiveness, we can revise this a bit.
So, the ideal way to write this would be something
like this, which is both shorter and has some
additional benefits like predictable exhaustiveness.
What is the difference here?
The first condition is still as above.
In the second condition it doesn't really matter or it isn't required
to check that t is greater than pi, because
we know the second line will only be checked
if this first line didn't hold.
So, we will only reach the second line if
the first condition wasn't true.
And since these are floating-point numbers,
we really know that if t is not smaller-equal
to pi, then t will be greater than pi.
So, actually, in this guard here, this check
is redundant in that sense.
That is because, anyway, we reach the second
line only if this first one was not valid.
And somewhat similarly, we can argue that
in the last line we don't have to check this,
because if this wouldn't be true, then we
would have already taken the case before that.
So, by writing "otherwise" here, we express
the same conditions, and we help the compiler
to know that this is a valid and full expression.
So, we avoided syntactic repetition, we avoided
redundant checks by exploiting the order and
what we know about exhaustiveness.
And in some way, I would argue that we also
made the definition more readable.
So, you might try to apply strategies like
this in your next exercise tasks, when you
have complex conditions like above.
Let us look at a few more examples and different
ways of writing definitions.
So far, we have always considered the case
that we basically have one "function head",
if you want, and then possibly several guards.
Actually, we can also write several lines
for a function definition.
So, instead of having "factorial n" and then
this guard and this guard, we could also have
this head several times.
So, saying: factorial n under the condition
that n equals zero is one, and factorial n
under the condition "otherwise" (which isn't
really a condition, because it is always true),
computes n * factorial (n – 1).
So, this would be equivalent to the versions
we have seen before.
Why would we even do this (to write this several
times)?
Well, thanks to the top-down evaluation order,
regarding selecting cases, we can then,
for example, write it also like this.
Which might be more appealing, to say: factorial
n under some condition is one, and factorial
n without any condition is this.
And since this evaluates from top to bottom,
it has the same semantics as what we have
written up here.
It's also, of course again, vulnerable to
changes of the order.
So, if we change orders here, then that might
completely change what is computed, or whether
it terminates.
Another syntactic difference or option is something like
a check like this: factorial n under the condition
that n equals zero, is something.
This condition "n == 0" in mathematics, you
would write differently.
You would simply say: factorial of zero is
one.
Instead of saying: factorial of n, if that
equals zero, is one.
Then we can write the first line also like
this.
And then, it really pays off that we write
several lines instead of relying on guards.
Here, we say: factorial of zero is one, and
factorial of n is this.
And since we check from top to bottom, actually
the last line means factorial for any non-zero
n, because zero is already dealt with here.
And this is now again something that you would
also find similarly written in a textbook
definition (in mathematics) of the factorial
function.
It says: factorial 0 is this and factorial
of n (in the background: for any other thing
than zero) is this expression.
You can mix these styles and find, for your
function that you want to express, what is
the nicest way to express the case distinctions
that you need for solving your problem.
This can be mixed.
So, let's look at another example, where we
have several input values and then we also
mix this kind of guard style and matching-against-constants
style.
This is such an example.
This is the Ackermann function that you might
know from your lecture on complexity theory.
And even if you don't, it is not really important.
It's a function that has some interesting
and complex conditions.
So, it has different base cases.
Either the first or the second input is zero,
but there are also some conditions on the
other input in each case.
You can express both, the matching against
the constant, but also the additional condition
on the other input.
And here we have the opposite way.
We have to check the condition by a constant match
on the second argument, and some explicitly
formulated constraint on the first input.
And there is also a case where we have numeric
checks on both inputs.
Then in each case we have some expression
that needs to be computed.
It doesn't really matter what the function
exactly does; the point is, we have this way
of expressing our conditions.
And again, this is matched from top to bottom.
So, if the first input is zero and the second
one is a non-negative number, then the first
base case will be taken.
And if you try this in GHC, then you will
get some interesting non-exhaustiveness warnings because
the compiler, here again, will try to find
out whether or not you have matched all cases
And well,
You might want to take a look at the warnings
and try to interpret them, to see how far
the compiler has managed to analyse this program
and the different cases that occur here.
That was just an example.
Let us actually return to some general remarks.
And this will be almost the end of this video.
So, let's recap what the general rules for
function definitions are.
We can have one or more equations.
We already started with one.
But now we have seen that we can have several
equations for one function.
And they will be checked from top to bottom.
And these equations can have guards, but they
don't have to have guards, as we have also just seen with the
factorial function.
There can be one or more arguments.
So far, these arguments will be variable names
on which maybe you want to express some conditions
via guards, or they can be constants like
zero or one that we have seen in some of the
examples.
The variable names can be anonymous.
That means, as you will see in an example
shortly on the last slide for today, we can
have cases where we can match against a variable,
but we will never use this variable again.
And then, in order not to have the compiler
complain that we named a variable that we
are not using, we can use the "_" as a variable
that we will never use.
This will be useful, as you will see on the
next slide.
Inside one equation, the variable names have
to be unique.
So, as we saw few slides back, we can have
two equations for factorial with the same
variable name, but these are different equations.
In one equation, we can't have two different
variable names.
We can't have ackermann of n and n (ackermann
n n).
We can have ackermann of n and m, but not
ackermann of n and n.
Because in one line, in one equation, the
variable names must be unique.
This does not apply to anonymous variables.
We can have several anonymous variables in
one line, and this does not somehow pose a
danger.
And finally, this is maybe not something that
you would try, but in case you would (because
maybe you have seen mathematical definitions
that use a feature like "solving conditions
on inputs via arithmetic expressions"):
what do i mean by this ? Something like a function definition in mathematics
which says, for example, f(2*n)= ... (something
which involves "f(n)"); this is a definition
kind that people sometimes write in mathematics
(because maybe they want to define a function
for all even integers, so, they say: f(2*n)=
...); but this is not something that Haskell
would accept.
Because then, Haskell would have to work out
from some given input like 12 whether or not this
matches 2*n.
So, Haskell would actually have to solve arithmetic
equations in a way that is not as generally
possible as one would want in a compiler.
So, this is not possible.
So, in these argument positions we can have
simple things, like constants, variable names,
later also some patterns over data types,
but not something like an arithmetic expression
of arbitrary kind, like 2*n.
Because that would require "solving" equations,
just for deciding which function definition
to take for a certain input situation.
This is just a side remark.
Let me actually finish by, mainly, showing
an example for this.
What do I mean by anonymous variables?
And why are they useful?
Well, let's consider this example.
So, let's say we want to define the logic operations
on the Boolean type.
We could say "not True = False" and "not False
= True".
But actually, in the second line we don't
have to write "not False = True", because
the only thing that can be here would be "False",
because "True" is already handled here.
Then we could say: Well, let's write "not
x = True", so using a variable named x here.
But this also would not be so nice, because
then the x is unused on the right-hand side.
And with certain settings, the compiler would
even complain that you introduce a variable
x but then in the scope you don't even make
use of the x.
And then the solution is "_", which basically
says "I don't care".
So, "not" of "True" is "False", and "not" of
whatever is "True", which, given the order
in which it is evaluated, is a perfect definition.
And it's also very intuitively written.
And similarly, you could proceed for other
logical operations.
So, let's say, for example, we want to implement
the conjunction of Boolean values.
Then we could say: "True and True is True",
and we could write three cases like "True
and False is False", "False and True is False",
and "False and False is False".
But why should we do this, if we can also
say: "whatever and whatever is False", given
that "True and True" has already been checked
by the first line?
Then this very compactly defines how conjunction
works.
And similarly, we could use a different style.
We could say: "b and True is b" and "whatever
and whatever is False".
Then we would handle two cases in the first
line.
It is maybe a matter of taste, a bit, which
of these two versions to choose in reality.
But it's not really important for your exercise
tasks.
In reality, there is a slight difference between
these two versions of the function, in particular
if you combine it with expensive computations
like the Ackermann function in one of the
argument positions.
But these will be cases that won't appear
in the ways you, for example, want to use
conjunction and combining conditions.
So, I will not talk further about this part.